<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the Parish-Church of Bridgewater, July 16, 1693, before the Right Reverend Father in God, Richard, Lord Bishop of Bath and Wells, at a confirmation by Fran. Prode ...</title>
            <author>Prowde, Francis, 1653 or 4-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6025</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13693875</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13693875</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56120)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 848:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the Parish-Church of Bridgewater, July 16, 1693, before the Right Reverend Father in God, Richard, Lord Bishop of Bath and Wells, at a confirmation by Fran. Prode ...</title>
                  <author>Prowde, Francis, 1653 or 4-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.H. for W. Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half title: Mr. Prowde's confirmation-sermon preached at Bridgewater, July 16, 1693.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Confirmation sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:101428:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101428:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Prowde</hi>'s Confirmation-Sermon, Preached at <hi>BRIDGEWATER,</hi> July 16. 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:101428:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>LAMBETH,</hi>
                  <date>Nov. 17. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Ra. Barker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101428:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Bridgewater, July</hi> 16. 1693. Before the Right Reverend Father in God, RICHARD, Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> AT A CONFIRMATION.</p>
            <p>By <hi>FRAN. PROWDE,</hi> M. A. Vicar of <hi>Woollavington</hi> in
<hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>W. Rogers,</hi> over againſt S.
<hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s-Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101428:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101428:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in God, RICHARD, LORD BISHOP of Bath and Wells.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE enſuing Diſcourſe, being ſolely the Product of your Lordſhip's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſeems naturally to fly to you for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage. I am very ſenſible it muſt meet with a great deal of that Goodneſs of Soul, and pious Inclination, which belongs to your Lordſhip, to render it acceptable: But the Deference I owe your Injunction, for having
<pb facs="tcp:101428:4"/>it made publick, encourages me to hope it may occaſion ſome good Thoughts and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours in the World: Which that it may, I heartily beg of God, and humbly ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your LORDSHIP's, Moſt Obedient Servant,</hi> Fran. Prowde.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101428:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS VIII. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then Laid they their Hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THAT reſult of the wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi>'s maturer thoughts, <hi>He that encreaſeth knowledge, encreaſeth ſorrow,</hi> is not more ſadly experimented, than while we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the religious ſtrifes which are ſo eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintain'd in the Chriſtian World. And among all the perplexing Controverſies of this unhappy nature, that about the Doctrine, which this Text of Scripture preſents to our conſideration, is not the leaſt. 'Tis ſtrange, even to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy, to conſider, that after the Office of Confirmation is ſo plainly deliver'd, and recommended in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; ſo religiouſly obſerved in the beſt and pureſt times of Chriſtianity; ſo generally own'd in the main, as to its nature and obligation, even by the moſt conſiderable Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties now among us, ſhould, after all, ſeem neglected and deſpis'd. What can be the occaſion of this melancholy ſcene of things? And whence muſt the contradiction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the evident grounds of this belief and practice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive? Indeed, what other reaſon can be given of it, but that the truly Primitive Spirit of Piety and Unity, with which the Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by viſiting theſe lower regions, bleſſed the world, is, for want of entertainment here, fled to Heaven. The Great and Incomprehenſible God has no dependence upon us; all his favours are free, and in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſenſe, unmerited by us. The methods of our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, though they are agreeable to our natures, and highly worthy our rational choice, yet they are aſſign'd us by God, and if we will be happy, we muſt make our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101428:5"/>ſelves ſo, as God has appointed. If through careleſneſs, or obſtinacy, we take wrong methods; and refuſe, or oppoſe thoſe which God has ordain'd, we then grieve and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his Holy Spirit, and unnaturally bring on our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and eternal ruine. Our compaſſionate Saviour, at his departure hence, promiſed us the comfortable aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, to the end of the World: And how the divine efflux ſhall be communicated, he himſelf, and the Pen-men of the New Teſtament, both by their precepts and examples have ſo plainly taught us, that in ſhort, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but our own perverſeneſs can undoe us. Particularly, in the words of my Text, according to the generality of the moſt learned and happy Interpreters of Sacred Writ, we have preſented to our thoughts, one of the admirable ways, or means, whereby the divine wiſdom has thought fit to convey both the outward, to wit, the extraordinary, and miraculous; and the inward, to wit, the ſaving and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gifts of the Holy Spirit. In ſhort, if we conſider the Context, it makes it clear beyond denial, that by Laying on of Hands, joyn'd with Prayer, and receiving the Holy Ghoſt, we are to underſtand the doctrine and effect of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation. For thoſe Prayers which we read were made by the Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> verſ. 15. did ſo ſoon at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Converſion and Baptiſm of the Chriſtians at <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> that it muſt ſignifie Confirmation.
<hi>When the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles which were at Jeruſalem</hi> (ſays the Text) <hi>heard that Samaria had received the word of God,</hi> and were baptized by <hi>Philip, they ſent unto them</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. which exactly agrees with this doctrine and uſage; being an act, which we find Primitively reſerv'd to the Rulers of the Church, and not allowed to inferiour Officers, ſuch as <hi>Philip</hi> the Deacon mention'd in this Chapter,<note place="margin">Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. verſ. 17.</note> though he was endowed with the miraculous gifts of the Holy Ghoſt. According to this notion Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> obſerves, that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101428:5"/>are call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<hi>Doctors,</hi> as that ſignifies the farther inſtructing them to whom the Goſpel hath been formerly preached; and as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> differs from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, preaching from teaching. And in Confirmation it certainly was, that in theſe firſt times of the Goſpel, both the ſaving, and miraculous gifts of the Holy Spirit us'd to be conferr'd. But beſides this, 'tis farther probable, that the Faith being planted at <hi>Samaria</hi> by <hi>Philip,</hi> and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles coming thither to Confirm, and not ſtaying there,<note place="margin">Acts 8. v. 25. Acts 14. v. 23. Tit. 1. v. 5.
<hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>ad</hi> Corin.</note> but returning to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they did, at their being there, ordain Elders, or Biſhops, in their ſeveral Cities; as we find <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did, and as we read <hi>Titus</hi> did alſo in <hi>Crete.</hi> This, ſays
<hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> the Apoſtles did in their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyings, when they went out preaching the Goſpel, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Preaching through Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and Cities, they conſtituted their Firſt-fruits, Biſhops and Deacons, of thoſe that ſhould afterwards believe.</hi> And thus, before this time, they had conſtituted <hi>James,</hi> the Brother of our Lord, Biſhop at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the firſt year after <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Aſcenſion: From whence it is not reaſonable to believe, that the Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> ſhould come down to <hi>Samaria,</hi> where the Goſpel had been ſo univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally receiv'd, and not alſo ordain ſome Governors over them before they returned. In ſhort, therefore, by Laying on of Hands, joyn'd with Prayer, and receiving the Holy Ghoſt, mention'd in my Text, both according to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, and general ſuffrage of Expoſitors, we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Confirmation, and Ordination; the Holy Ghoſt, by the Apoſtle's miniſtry, coming on all the ſincere believers, and endowing them with the internal, ſaving and laſting gifts of the Holy Spirit, and ſome of them with external and miraculous powers. And the Apoſtles alſo, by Laying on their Hands on ſome ſignalized perſons, Ordain'd them Biſhops, and Deacons, in ſeveral Cities; the Power of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101428:6"/>doing which belong'd only to the Apoſtles to exerciſe, and was not
<hi>Philip</hi>'s buſineſs, though he had power to preach, and baptize; nay though himſelf was endow'd with mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous gifts. Now theſe things premis'd, in accounting for my Text, and in reference to the preſent occaſion, I ſhall purſue this following method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall endeavour to give a true, and diſtinct Account, of the Doctrine of Confirmation, obſerving whence it deriv'd, how it obtain'd, and has been practis'd in the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall briefly obſerve the qualification of the Perſon, to whom originally the Adminiſtration of it ſeems to have been aſſign'd.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall anſwer ſome Objections, which are brought againſt it. And,</p>
            <p n="4">4. and Laſtly, by way of Application, I ſhall propound ſome Conſiderations, evincing the Reaſonableneſs, Divine Excellency, and Neceſſity of its Practice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> To begin with the <hi>Firſt</hi> of theſe Particulars; to wit, to preſent a true, and diſtinct Account of the Doctrine of Confirmation, obſerving whence it deriv'd, how it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, and has been practiſed in the Church. The learned <hi>Grotius</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Grot. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. Cap.</hi> 6. Paul. <hi>ad</hi> Hebr. <hi>v.</hi>
2.</note> that Impoſition of Hands, joyn'd with Prayer, was peculiarly us'd in the Primitive Chriſtian Church, in theſe five following Caſes. <hi>Baptizatis ad ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinendam vim confirmantem ſpiritus ſancti; ordinatis ad Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterium; poſt peccata reconciliatis; Corpore infirmis; imò &amp; novis conjugibus benedictionem ab Eccleſiâ poſtulantibus;</hi> i. e. <hi>To thoſe who have been baptiz'd, in order to obtain the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming Influence of the holy Spirit; in ordination; to the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; in caſes of ſickneſs; and to the newly married:</hi> And moſt of theſe, if not all (as he hints) deriving from Hebrew Cuſtoms; and to this purpoſe, we find it recorded in theſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101428:6"/>following parts of Divine Writ: <hi>Gen.</hi> 48. Verſ. 14, 15, and 16. <hi>And Iſrael ſtretched out his right hand, and laid it on Ephraim's head, who was the younger; and his left hand upon Manaſſes's head; guiding his hands wittingly, for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes was the firſt born. And he bleſſed Joſeph, and ſaid, God before whom my Fathers, Abraham, and Iſaac, did walk; the God that fed me all my life long, bleſs the Lads.</hi> Here we find the Laying on of the Hand joyned with Prayer, uſed to conferr Divine Grace. Thus we likewiſe find it practiſed, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. verſ. 27. being an Account of that ſacred Form of Bleſſing, wherewith, God himſelf taught <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his Sons, to bleſs the Children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Our Engliſh Tranſlation reads it, <hi>They ſhall put my name upon the Children of Iſrael, and I will bleſs them. Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremellius</hi> paraphraſe the words: <hi>Et imponentes manus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis Iſraelis, invocabunt nomen meum, &amp; ego benedicam eis:</hi> Putting their Hands on the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they ſhall pray to me for them, and I will bleſs them. And in their Notes on this Text of Scripture, they add farther, in theſe words; <hi>duobus ſignis teſtatum facient Populo meo gratiam meam, &amp;c.</hi> By theſe two Signs, Calling on my Name, and the ſolemn Laying on of their own Hands, they ſhall aſſure my People of that Grace, which I, according to my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, will beſtow upon them. And this Grace, or the Effect of this Bleſſing, as the Learned Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi> obſerves,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Aqua g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis.</note> from ſome of the Jewiſh <hi>Rabbins,</hi> uſed to be called the Weapons, and Armour of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe, we read <hi>Numb.</hi> 8. verſ. 10, 11, and 14. <hi>Thou ſhalt bring the Levites before the Lord; and the Children of Iſrael ſhall put their hands upon the Levites; and Aaron ſhall offer the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites before the Lord; thus ſhalt thou ſeparate the Levites, from among the Children of Iſrael, and the Levites ſhall be mine.</hi> I ſhall onely add one inſtance more, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27. verſ. 18. That when <hi>Moſes</hi> was to leave the World; and his trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101428:7"/>Charge, the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> he was order'd by God himſelf, to conſtitute <hi>Joſhua</hi> his Succeſſour, after this Manner: <hi>And the Lord</hi> (ſays the Text) <hi>ſaid unto Moſes, take thee Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua, the Son of Nun, a Man in whom is the Spirit, and Lay thine Hand upon him.</hi> I might inſtance in other Paſſages to this ſame purpoſe; but theſe are ſufficient to point to us, whence the Sacred uſage of Impoſition of Hands, in the Chriſtian Church deriv'd its Original. And to apply this more particularly to our preſent Caſe: The <hi>Jews,</hi> having circumciſed their Children at Eight days old, ſo ſoon as they were capable of inſtruction, they took the greateſt care of them imaginable; particularly, when their Sons were five Years old, they inſtructed them in the Text of the Law; when they were ten Years old, they put them to the Text of the <hi>Talmud,</hi> and when they arriv'd at Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, they were publickly preſented in an holy Aſſembly; there ſolemnly to oblige themſelves to be <hi>Filii praecepti,</hi> ſubject to the Law; to keep the
<hi>Paſcha, Sabbath,</hi> and the reſt of their Ceremonies;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Veem</hi>'s
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>epoſit. of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Moral
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w. <hi>Bux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rf. Syn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>daic.</hi>
               </note> thence forward, they were to anſwer for their own Sins; and hereupon, Prayer was made for them, with the Impoſition of the High-Prieſt's hands, in order to the conferring Divine ſtrength. In ſhort, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to theſe, and ſuch uſages, during the Patriarchal, and Moſaick Oeconomies, we find it practis'd under the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Diſpenſation. For by Laying on of Hands, as an appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory Sign, join'd with Prayer, did our Saviour, and his immediate Followers, heal Diſeaſes. Thus our Bleſſed Lord demean'd himſelf toward the Children which came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; he put his hands upon them, and bleſſed them, praiſing their inoffenſive, and unprejudic'd Tempers, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling that happy, habit of Thoughts, which diſpoſes to the Entertainment of his Divine Religion: This Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hands, join'd with Prayer, we read our Saviour's Apoſtles evidently practis'd.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ts 6. v. 1.</note> Thus they inveſted the ſeven
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101428:7"/>Deacons in their Office; thus <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> at
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> were conſecrated to that Divine undertaking, which God had aſſign'd them. Thus <hi>Timothy</hi> was ordain'd Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; and thus all along, in the Apoſtles Times, it was an unqueſtionable, and allow'd way to bleſs, conſecrate, and conferr Grace, by Prayer, and the Laying on of Hands. And thus particularly, in reference to Confirmation, theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Texts of Scripture are almoſt Univerſally inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, as Precedents for our Inſtruction. And (not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on my Text, which I have already explain'd) thus we read, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. verſ. 5, 6. <hi>When they heard this, they were baptiz'd in the Name of the Lord Jeſus; and when Paul had Laid his Hands upon them, the Holy Ghoſt came on them, and they ſpake with Tongues and propheſied.</hi> Indeed, we find mention'd here, onely the miraculous Effects of the Holy Ghoſt, they being abſolutely neceſſary then, and allowed by the Divine Power, and Wiſdom, for the infant State of the Church. But as the ſaving Gifts of the Holy Spirit, were promis'd by our Saviour to the End of the World, and were ever neceſſary; ſo it muſt be allow'd, That they were then conferr'd, though the External operations, which preſently demonſtrated their Collation, perhaps for that Reaſon onely, are particulariz'd: But farther, the Doctrine of Confirmation is plainly recorded in <hi>Hebrews</hi> 6. verſ. 2.
<hi>Therefore</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle in the Firſt Verſe of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) <hi>leaving the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, let us go on unto perfection; not laying again the foundation of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from dead Works, and of faith toward God, of the Doctrine of Baptiſms, and Laying on of Hands, and of Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead, and of Eternal Judgment.</hi> Here, we find the Doctrine of Confirmation placed among the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and moſt neceſſary Chriſtian Truths, ſuch as are Eſſentials of our Religion, Faith, Repentance, Baptiſm, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Dead, and Eternal Judgment. And it muſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101428:8"/>neceſſarily follow from this Text of Scripture, That either the Doctrine of Confirmation is not here deſign'd by the Apoſtle, which is contrary to the general Sence of Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors: Or elſe we muſt inferr, That the Apoſtle rank'd theſe Chriſtian Doctrines very unagreeably, which is a too ſtrangely ſevere Reflection upon the great Apoſtle: Or elſe we muſt conclude, That we are hence obliged to pay an extraordinary Deference to this Apoſtolical uſage; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, and eſteeming it, as one of the happy Advances toward Heaven, which the Divine Wiſdom has aſſign'd us. Now according to theſe, and other Texts of Scripture in the New Teſtament, thoſe that were baptiz'd in the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chriſtian Church; Adult Perſons, ſoon after Baptiſm; Children, when being taught, and capable of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Principles of Chriſtian Religion, were brought to the Biſhop, publickly to acknowledge, and confirm their baptiſmal Vow; and by Laying on of the Biſhop's Hand, join'd with devout Prayer for them, were bleſs'd by him, in order to their growing in Grace, and the knowledge of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>ad</hi> Jul.</note> This, in ſhort, is the uſage, which <hi>Cyprian</hi> declares, was continued in the Church, from the Apoſtles Time, and Example, who mentioning the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> baptiz'd by <hi>Philip,</hi> and afterwards Confirm'd by <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> (as we read in my Text) tells us, that they who in the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> have receiv'd Baptiſm, 'tis ſtill the Cuſtom, that they be offer'd; <hi>And by our Prayers,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and the Laying on of our Hands, receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Book I. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Marcion. Contra</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cif.</note> 
               <hi>The fleſh</hi> (ſays <hi>Tertullian</hi>) <hi>by Impoſition of Hands, is ſhadowed, that the Soul, by the Spirit, may be illuminated.</hi> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> having declared, that by the <hi>Impoſition of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized Hands, and Prayer, the Holy Ghoſt was ſtill convey'd to the Baptiz'd,</hi> expoſtulates thus, <hi>Doſt thou ask me where it is written? I anſwer, in the Acts of the Holy Apoſtles.</hi> But if there <hi>were not ſo plain Authority of Scripture for it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101428:8"/>the Practice of the whole Chriſtian World in this particular, might challenge the force of a Command.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on this Subject, expreſſes himſelf thus;<note place="margin">Rhemiſt<hi>'s Teſta.</hi> Acts 8.</note> 
               <hi>Is there any Man of ſo perverſe an heart, as to deny thoſe Children on whom we Impoſe Hands in Confirmation, to have receiv'd the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe they ſpeak not with Tongues, as was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and agreeable to the Times when the Goſpel was firſt planted?</hi> To theſe I might add the Suffrages of many more; but this Account of the Doctrine of Confirmation from Antiquity, is ſo apparent, and has been ſo often, and ſo learnedly perform'd, that I own my ſelf obliged to Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize, for pretending to it: I ſhall therefore onely add theſe two Remarks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That 'tis obſervable,<note place="margin">Cornel. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium
<hi>apud</hi> Euſeb. Opt. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>cont.</hi> Par.</note> that the firſt oppoſers of this Doctrine, were the <hi>Novatians,</hi> and the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis likewiſe obſervable, that no one in the Primitive Church, was admitted to the Sacrament of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, without Confirmation. And ſo great a Veneration, had the then Chriſtian World for that Sacrament; that there was no publick Aſſembly for the Worſhip of God, without a Communion: And as this particular Chriſtian Zeal, began to decline, Impiety, and Wickedneſs, gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally prevail'd. But while I inſiſt on this particular, I ſhall briefly obſerve, that this Chriſtian uſage, has been recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to our Practice, by Proteſtants of the greateſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, even among all Parties.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apol.</hi> part.
<hi>4.</hi> de Baptiſ. puer.</note> The <hi>Waldenſes</hi> in their Apology to the Marquiſs of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> 1532. ſpeaking of Children which have been baptiz'd, thus expreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>When they are come to years of underſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſ. <hi>Waldenſ.</hi> de Confir.</note> 
               <hi>and can give a competent Account of their Faith, and begin truly to love Chriſt; we bring them to profeſs theſe things, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their Parents, or Godfathers, or the Church, have taught them: that on their own accord, they may make a free profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all theſe things, before the whole Church, to their own
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101428:9"/>Salvation, in the Celebration of the Office of Impoſition of Hands:</hi> Which being performed, <hi>they are Confirm'd by the Biſhop.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſ.
<hi>Waldenſ.</hi> de Confir. <hi>Chem</hi> Ex. Concil. <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi> de Confir.</note> And this they tell us, was obſerv'd in the Times of the Apoſtles: Thus likewiſe,
<hi>Chemnitius,</hi> that extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Perſon, accounts for this Doctrine, as 'twas held by the Proteſtant Churches in general. <hi>Noſtri ſaepè oſtende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Our Divines have often prov'd, that the Rite of Confirmation, being ſeparated from Popiſh Superſtitions, might be very happily us'd, even according to the Holy Scriptures, that thoſe who have been baptiz'd in their Infancy, when they come to years of diſcretion, ſhould be carefully taught the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church, in ſome ſhort, and eaſie Catechiſm: and when they are found in ſome competent meaſure to underſtand it; that then they be brought to the Biſhop, and the Church;</hi> and that the Child, who in his Infancy was baptiz'd, ſhould,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In ſhort, be put in mind of his Baptiſm; what was then beſtow'd upon him, and what he likewiſe then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to doe, that he would renounce the Devil, profeſs the Chriſtian Faith, and endeavour after all Holy Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Child publickly before the Congregation, own this Faith.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That there be added a ſerious Exhortation out of God's Word, That he will continue in that Covenant which he made in Baptiſm, and that Faith, and Doctrine, which he then profeſſed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That publick Prayer be made for thoſe Children; That God would govern, preſerve, and confirm them in that Profeſſion by his Holy Spirit: At which Prayer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Superſtition, may be uſed the Putting on of Hands. Neither would ſuch a Prayer (ſays he) be to no purpoſe; for 'tis warranted upon the Conſideration of the Gift of perſeverance, and the Confirming Grace. Such a Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation (ſays he) would afford great Advantage, both to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101428:9"/>the younger Sort, and the whole Church: And then he goes on to prove how agreeable this would be to Scripture, proving ſeveral particulars out of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, Chap. 8, 14, 19. and from ſeveral Canons, made in ſeveral Councils, much to the ſame purpoſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melanct.</hi> Confeſſ. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiarum <hi>Sax.</hi> cap. de Confirm. <hi>Hemin. Syntag.</hi> cap. <hi>22. Calv.</hi> Inſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c
<hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Melancthon</hi> declares for this uſage, in the Churches of
<hi>Saxony;</hi> and <hi>Hemingius</hi> for thoſe of <hi>Denmark;</hi> thus likewiſe Mr.
<hi>Calvin, Hic mos olim fuit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It hath been an Ancient Cuſtom, that Children being inſtructed in an eaſie, and ſhort Catechiſm, ſhould be brought to the Biſhop to be confirmed by him.</hi> And in his Commentary on <hi>Hebrews</hi> 6. he has theſe words.
<hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actâ Infantiâ,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Their Infancy paſſed over, and being cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized, Children were admitted to the ſymbol of Impoſition of Hands;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> and this one place of Scripture (ſays Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>) plainly proves, that this practice derived from the Apoſtles: and in another place, he has theſe words; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam verò morem hunc,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Would to God we might retain this Cuſtom:</hi> Of the ſame Judgment with theſe, I find <hi>Beza, Piſcator, Marloret,</hi> and ſeveral others. And here, not to mention the extraordinary Zeal for this Doctrine, declared by the many great Men of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Piety, is famous throughout the Chriſtian World: I ſay not to mention theſe in our own Cauſe; I ſhall onely in ſhort, remark two Inſtances more, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this caſe; and that of the Aſſembly in their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> p. 102. in his Tract on Confirmation, beſides many other to the ſame End, has theſe Words.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. (Says he) <hi>We find in Scripture, a Bleſſing of Church-Members, with Laying on of Hands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>We find in Scripture, that the Holy Ghoſt, is in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner, promiſed to believers, over and above that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Spirit, which cauſed them to believe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>We find, that Prayer, with Laying on of Hands, was the outward means to be uſed by Chriſt's Miniſters, for the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this Bleſſing.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101428:10"/>
               <item>4. <hi>We ſind, that this was a fixed Ordinance to the Church, and not a temporary thing:</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> declares his Judgment. The Aſſembly in their Annotations expreſs themſelves thus: <hi>Laying on of Hands, which is uſually called Confirmation, conſiſted.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>In examining thoſe who had been baptized, what progreſs they had made in the Doctrine of Chriſtianity.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>In praying for them, that God would continue them in the Faith; and give them more Grace, ſtrengthening them by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now, when the Chief Paſtour, or Paſtours of the Church, prayed for them, they Laid their Hands upon them; whence the Apoſtolical Conſtitution was called Laying on of Hands; ſo they, ſo St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and ſo moſt of the Fathers, with one Conſent. Now from all this, I hope I may juſtly inferr, and that even from the Confeſſion of ſome of thoſe, who have been unhappily prejudiced againſt our Communion, That the deſign and uſage of the Church, in the caſe of Confirmation, owes it ſelf to a pious, and judicious Reſpect; to a truly Ancient, and Apoſtolical Inſtitution, practiſed, and recommended, in all ſucceeding Ages of the Church, as a Means of conferring farther ſpiritual ſtrength, and the Advancements of Divine Grace: To impreſs upon tender, and capable Thoughts, a ſignal and laſting Reverence, and Dread of the Divine Majeſty, and an agreeable Care, and Concern for that Holy Religion, which, they eſpouſed in their Baptiſm, by the Means of others.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> But I proceed to the <hi>Second</hi> particular, briefly to obſerve the qualification of the Perſons, to whom the adminiſtring of Confirmation, ſeems to have been originally aſſigned. And here, 'tis much more than probable, that according to Apoſtolical Example, and all along after the Apoſtles, till of very late Years; the Office of Confirmation, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101428:10"/>performed by the chief Governours of the Church, called Biſhops. 'Tis very evident, that our Bleſſed Lord himſelf, made an original diſtinction among thoſe, whom he conſtituted, and ordained Officers in ins Church. He well knew, that an Imparity in Church Officers naturally promotes peace, would lay a Foundation for that Unity, which he all along ſo highly recommends, and which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed belongs to the. Nature and Deſign of that happy Religion which he came to eſtabliſh and promote in the World. To this purpoſe we find the plain Diſtinction of twelve Apoſtles, and ſeventy, or ſeventy two Diſciples. When one of the ſelect Twelve betrayed his Maſter, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately one of the Seventy was choſen in his place. Now if the Office of theſe, and their Power in the Church were the ſame, why do we meet with this Diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Apoſtles and Diſciples? Some Inequality of Order and Power, in the then Officers of the Church, we muſt hence diſcover; and that likewiſe inſtituted by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf. This Diſtinction which is founded even in the Nature of Things, and is ſo abſolutely neceſſary in the World, could not be forgot by our Bleſſed Lord, who knew all things now agreeably to this Notion; to go no farther than my Text, and the preceding Verſes, we read, that when the Apoſtles, to whom the Power of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the Church then belonged, (being at
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) heard that <hi>Samaria</hi> had received the Word of God; they immediately ſent two of their own Number, to wit, St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>John,</hi> to adminiſter Confirmation. For though we read that the <hi>Samaritans</hi> were baptized by <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> and that his Miraculous Works among them, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated him to be a very extraordinary Perſon; yet 'tis evident, this did not qualifie him for adminiſtring Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that being an Office, which then belonged to the Apoſtles, by reaſon of that Superiority over the then In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101428:11"/>Church, our Saviour had inveſted them with: And which according to this his firſt Inſtitution, was all along after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards continued in a Succeſſion of Biſhops.
<hi>Blondel</hi> and <hi>Salmaſius</hi> themſelves, the great and learned Defenders of Presbytery, own Biſhops to have been accounted Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to Presbyters, even in the next Age to the Apoſtles: But this they labour to prove, was an Incroachment of Epiſcopacy. But whoever ſincerely reads their Writings, and the Famous <hi>Monſieur Daillé,</hi> on the ſame Subject, will find ſuch ſtruggles of Thought, and forcing of Argument; in ſhort, ſuch obſtinate Reſolves to maintain a Cauſe, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of disapproving, recommends the Truth they deſign to baffle. Particularly, whoever calmly obſerves Mr. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>illé</hi> s violent Efforts againſt <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Epiſtles, which clearly give the Cauſe for Epiſcopacy, muſt needs own, that he never ſaw Opinion more ſtrangely prevail againſt Truth, and Judgment. For that great Man, obſerving ſeveral of <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſtles, deſcribing the Conſtitution of the Hierarchy, in his Time, by the ſeveral diſtinct Orders of Biſhop, Presbyter and Deacon, is ſo extremely furious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, that rather than drop his own dear Opinion, he offers ſuch Arguments, as, indeed, reflect upon all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, even the Sacred Canon of Scripture it ſelf not excepted. But having briefly hinted thus much, I might proceed to ſhew, that according to this Superiority of Order, and Office, this right of governing the Church, which was firſt lodg'd in the Apoſtles of our Saviour, and wherewith the Biſhops were after them, <hi>de facto,</hi> inveſted: (I ſay) according to this Primitive Cuſtom, and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was the Adminiſtration of Confirmation, aſſigned to Epiſcopacy, in the ſucceeding Ages of the Church. To this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Dialog. adverſ.
<hi>Lucif.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Hierom</hi> tells us, That <hi>non niſi per manus Epiſcopi,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>By the Hands of the Biſhop onely, was Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation adminiſtred.</hi> But waving this Sort of Proof; I ſhall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101428:11"/>onely add the plain Confeſſions in this Caſe, of ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who were far from being intereſted in the Epiſcopal Cauſe. <hi>Hic mos olim fuit, ut Chriſtianorum liberi, poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam adoleverant, coram Epiſcopo ſiſterentur</hi> (ſays Mr.
<hi>Calvin;</hi>) <hi>It was the Ancient Cuſtom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſtit. l. c.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for the Children of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parents, when they were fit for Confirmation, to be brought before the Biſhop:</hi> And, <hi>They are certainly to be condemned of groſs Partiality, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs</hi> (ſay s Mr. <hi>Hanmer</hi>) <hi>who bluſh not to ſay, that the Biſhops out of pride,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> on Confirm. <hi>p.</hi> 51.</note> 
               <hi>have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to themſelves, the Laying on of Hands in Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> And that Mr.
<hi>Baxter</hi> allows this Rite, to have been all along, generally adminiſtred by Biſhops, muſt needs be evident to any one who reads his Book on Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation; where he labours to prove, that though Biſhops did Anciently officiate in this Caſe; yet that Presbyters might do it, the Nature of the Thing, and Neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring. Thus theſe unhappy Oppoſers of Epiſcopacy, have recorded their Judgments: But after all, ſuch is the Moderation of the pureſt, and beſt conſtituted Church in the World, I mean the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in this Caſe, that ſo the Divine End, and Deſign of Confirmation be accompliſhed, ſhe does not cenſure thoſe Churches, which want Proteſtant Biſhops.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> I proceed to the <hi>Third</hi> particular I propounded; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſome Objections, which are brought againſt this Uſage. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some will not permit Confirmation to derive from Apoſtolica) Example; and though the Primitive Church entertain'd it as ſuch a Doctrine, yet (ſay they) it was theirs, and has been all along ſince, a groſs Miſtake. Thus I find Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> on the
<hi>Rhemiſt</hi>'s Teſtament, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers arguing. Their main Argument is, That thoſe Texts of Scripture, which are brought for Confirmation, are all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101428:12"/>to be interpreted, onely of conferring the Miraculous Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt: And that when theſe Gifts ceaſed in the Church, Confirmation vainly had its beginning. To which in ſhort, it may be anſwered; That it is clear even beyond denial, that the Laying on of Hands, joyn'd with Prayer, was uſed in the conferring Grace, or Divine Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, long before the Apoſtles Times. And farther, it can never be proved, that onely the Miraculous Gifts of the Holy Spirit, were given by the Apoſtles, in their Laying on of Hands. But as the internal, ſaving Gifts of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, were more neceſſary in their own Nature, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by our Saviour to the End of the World; ſo they muſt be given by the Apoſtles; and thence Confirmation obtained in the Chriſtian Church.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Baptiſ. Cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> It is not now (ſays St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>), as it was, that by the Teſtimony of temporal, and ſenſible Miracles, the Holy Ghoſt is by the Impoſition of Hands, given as formerly, to recommend and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Truth of the then new Chriſtian Faith, and for the Enlargement of the lately begun Church; for who (as he expoſtulates) does now expect, that thoſe upon whom Hands are Impoſed, for the receiving the Holy Ghoſt, ſhould ſuddenly begin to ſpeak with Tongues? But inviſibly (ſays he) is the Love of God inſpired into their Hearts. Thus St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> anſwers this Objection. But, indeed, 'tis very plain, that the Prejudice of Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> and others, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Doctrine, derives from their Abhorrence of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Superſtition. For,</p>
            <p>This is evident from their Writings, and this leads me to a <hi>Second</hi> Objection againſt Confirmation, that it is a Popiſh uſage, and a Compliance with the Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and this tho' contrary to all reaſon, has prejudiced too many againſt it. Indeed it muſt be confeſſed, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has made Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation a Sacrament; nay, has gone farther, preferred it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101428:12"/>to Baptiſm, made it conſiſt in <hi>opere operato,</hi> beſtowed it on Infants, and clogged it with ſeveral unneceſſary Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. In ſhort, as they have done in other matters, ſo they have robb'd it of its Apoſtolical Primitive Deſign, and Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and expoſed it under a falſe Notion, and in an antick Garb. But if this may be lawfully argued againſt Confirmation, when 'tis rightly uſed, and applyed; then muſt we caſt off the Sacraments of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper. In ſhort, reject Chriſtianity it ſelf, becauſe all, or moſt of its admirable Doctrines, have been abuſed and debauched by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For whoever ſeriouſly inquires into the nature of it, will certainly find, that the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as it differences it ſelf from us, is really made up of nothing but folly, and contradiction to the Divine deſign of Chriſtianity. But to return; the Church of <hi>England</hi> having removed from Confirmation all popiſh Superſtition, and Pretences to a Sacrament; and having ordered a preparatory Catechiſm for all thoſe to learn, and competently to underſtand, who ſhall be admitted to it. In ſhort, having taken all poſſible care to anſwer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of its Primitive Inſtitution, to impreſs upon the thoughts of youth, a great and laſting Veneration for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, obliges them to conſider, and reaſſume in their own Perſons, what their Sureties promiſed for them in their Baptiſm. In ſhort, that they will believe, and behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as becomes Chriſtians. Theſe things premiſed, they are by fervent Prayer, attended with the Apoſtolical ſign of Laying on of Hands, recommended to God, and the happy Effects of their own pious reſolves. Now, if this be a true (tho' ſhort) account of the Church of <hi>England's</hi> deſign in Confirmation, how unreaſonable is it, for any one to object againſt it; as Popiſh and Superſtitious. But I ſhall conclude this Objection with an agreeable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I find in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Poſtſcript to his Tract on Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101428:13"/>
               <hi>Some will ſay</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it is mere Prelacy, or a Prelatical deſign, and ſome that it is Independancy, or an Independant deſign; and ſome that it is but Presbyterian Examination: whereas they might know that it is proper to none of them, which is common to them all? If it be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, how comes it to be found with Independants? If if be Independancy, how comes it to be approved by Prelates, and Preſbyterians? Is it not rather like Chriſtianity it ſelf, and the Truths and Duties we commonly own; and therefore, not to be appropriated to any.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> preſſed on with the mighty force of Truth, anſwers this Objection. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſaddeſt occaſion of the moſt prevailing Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt this Primitive uſage, is, The evident want of an hearty, and true concern for Religion for alas, inſtead of the Primitive Chriſtian Spirit of Piety and Unity, a careleſs and prophane Temper, or a furious, and irregular Zeal, have too apparently got the aſcendant in our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> world. Hence we are too generally prejudiced againſt our Happineſs, and hence all our great misfortunes derive: to be really a Chriſtian, is to be in love with all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine methods which lead us to Heaven; to be ſincerely devoted to all the genuine Acts of Piety, Juſtice and Sobriety, to practiſe whatever is acceptable to God, love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among Men, and agreeable to the rational deſigns of our Natures. Theſe things demonſtrate us Chriſtians; would make us happy here, and introduce an habit of thoughts, in ſome degree reſembling the bleſſed Spirits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove; would lay the Foundation of our preſent, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Bliſs; would oblige us to comply with all the means of Salvation, which are aſſign'd us by our God. But while we are not in earneſt with God Almighty; nor ſincerely reſolved in our choice of Happineſs; 'tis no wonder we neglect, or deſpiſe the methods, which ſhould
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101428:13"/>advance us to Heaven; 'tis indeed no wonder we loath our Duties here; and undo our ſelves for ever. But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving briefly reflected on thoſe Objections,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> I proceed to the <hi>Fourth</hi> and Laſt particular, To propound ſome Conſiderations, evincing the Reaſonableneſs, divine Excellency, and neceſſity of this uſage. And here,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us look back into the Primitive times of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; and view this Practice then prevailing, when the true Chriſtian Spirit, and Temper, was warm and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, when the holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> had newly bleſſed the world, with his Preſence and his Miracles; when in the Infant ſtate of our Religion, men did not quarrel with their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but being influenced by heavenly Demonſtration, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed here as it becomes Chriſtians, and longed to be where their Lord was gone. Now either we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn theſe happy times; or we muſt own our ſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to pay an extraordinary deference to this Primitive Doctrine. If this Conſideration don't awaken our thoughts, what can rouze us from our ſinful ſlumber? 'Tis unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable, that theſe Firſt profeſſours of Chriſtianity, were really what they pretended, profeſſing a moſt holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and living according to their Profeſſion, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this world; and having their thoughts fired with a Deſire, and Expectation of a better Life; ſo perfectly holy was their Faith, that it demonſtrated it ſelf to come from Heaven; and ſo agreeable was their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation to their belief, that it proved their Example to be divine. Should we not therefore be highly concerned to tread in their ſteps; and to uſe the ſame heavenly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, which they have uſed and taught us? if we don't how can we pleaſe our ſelves in their hopes; and be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of their Happineſs? But,</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101428:14"/>
            <p n="2">2. We may ſadly conſider, That our forſaking, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting this holy Uſage, and Doctrine, does not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict Antiquity, reflect upon the Apoſtles, and the firſt and beſt Chriſtians; but lays the Foundation for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacy of our Age, and the Ruine of Religion among us; did we only conſider the Doctrine of Confirmation, as recommended by the Firſt, and beſt Ages of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church; this muſt needs repreſent it as a Duty not to be neglected by us; but of ſuch fatal Tendency is the diſuſe of it, that it demonſtrates that diſuſe, not only contrary to Apoſtolical and Primitive example, but a contradiction lodged in the Nature of things, againſt the heavenly deſign of Chriſtianity. For how evident is it, that while Confirmation is neglected, the Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Children is neglected too? When ſuch a ſolemn and publick tryal of Youth, as Confirmation is, ſeems by diſuſe to be laid aſide, how unconcerned are Parents apt to be for their Children, and Children for themſelves? How generally is that ſacred Vow forgotten, which Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties made for Children at their Baptiſm? and how little impreſſion does the infant Vow make upon the Child? while this holy Obligation is not ſolemnly profeſſed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſumed at Confirmation, how apt are we to rank our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Vow among the Dreams of our Infancy; among the to-be-forgotten things of our unthinking Age? and what muſt naturally follow this neglect, but Ignorance Diviſions, and prophane Atheiſm? for while in order to Confirmation, Children are not inſtructed in the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion; they are expoſed to all theſe dreadful misfortunes: Either to fall into a ſinful Lethargy, for want of divine Inſtruction; or inſtead of a rational ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Piety, to be hurried away with a religious Frenzy; or laſtly, to loſe the Happineſs both of this, and a far better world, by the wild Inconſiſtencies of Atheiſm and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101428:14"/>Prophaneneſs. Thus does the neglect of Confirmation, and an agreeable preparation for it, evidently occaſion, either a ſtupid Ignorance, or a miſapprehenſion, or an open af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting of the great Creator, and Governour of the world: In ſhort, whoever ſeriouſly reflects on theſe diſmal Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, and has not loſt all concern for Religion, muſt needs deeply reſent the ſtrange indifferency, which this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Inſtitution has met with among us; that it looks very ominous, even like one of thoſe preſages of divine Diſpleaſure, before the <hi>Migremus hinc</hi> was heard in the laſt Temple of the <hi>Jews;</hi> for indeed according to this melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly parallel between the
<hi>Jews</hi> and us, 'tis Preſumption and not Faith, to expect God to be with us, if we deſpiſe or neglect his Ordinances. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. And laſtly, We may very pertinently conſider, the many and extraordinary advantages of the genuine uſe of this Doctrine, which becauſe they have been ſo often, and admirably expreſſed by great Men of our own Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; I ſhall therefore among the reſt, chuſe to repreſent it you, in the few, tho' compleat words of the judicious <hi>Hooker: By the means of Confirmation</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it comes to paſs, that Children in the expectation of it are ſeaſon'd with Principles of true Religion, before evil, and corrupt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples deprave their Minds; a good Foundation is laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, for direction of the Courſe of their Lives; the ſeed of the Church of God, is preſerved ſincere and found; the Prelates and Fathers of God's Family, to whom the care of their Souls belongs, ſo by Tryal, and Examination of them apart, of their own heavy burden diſcharged, reap comfort, by beholding the firſt beginnings of true Godlineſs in tender years, and neglect not ſo fit an opportunity of giving every one Fatherly encouragement and exhortation; whereunto Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Hands, and Prayer being added, our Warrant for the great good effect thereof, is the ſame which Patriarchs,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101428:15"/>Prophets, Prieſts, Apoſtles, Fathers, and Men of God in all ages, have had for ſuch their Benedictions.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelf in this caſe, and that I may repreſent it more particularly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the due uſe of Confirmation, the diligent Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing of Children, would be happily promoted; than which, nothing would more truely advance the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſign of our moſt holy Religion. For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. By this means Parents, and Sureties would be awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a ſenſe of their Duty, even thoſe Parents, and Sureties, whom the Principles of Piety don't influence, would be obliged into a concern for their Duty, leſt their remiſsneſs ſhould prove their ſhame; leſt thoſe Children they were concerned to have inſtructed, ſhould by their Ignorance be unfit for Confirmation; and conſequently the imputation of that Ignorance belong to them. Thus would the ſenſe of preſent ſhame awaken thoſe thoughts, which are unconcerned at the proſpect of eternal confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for how little ſoever of this pious Concern, we meet with in the world, theſe Obligations and Vows, will be ſtrictly enquired after at the Day of Judgment; the Parent, and Surety, muſt give a ſad account of that Child, which by their negligence is eternally ruined; how natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral a Puniſhment is confuſion, and torment of thought, to ſuch a Crime as this? What can more aggravate the Miſery of the damned, than to reflect, they have brought others into their place of torment? Nay, how peculiarly cloſe muſt this pain of thought ſtick to that Parent, who is forced to animadvert, he has for ever undone his own Off-ſpring?</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the due uſe of Confirmation, Children themſelves would out of a pleaſant, pious Emulation, happily enquire after Divine knowledge, in order to their being Confirmed, would endeavour to know Chriſtianity betimes. Thus
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101428:15"/>might thoſe little ambitious thoughts, which generally ſhew themſelves in theſe tender years, be diſpoſed to a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine contrivance; even to lay a Foundation for Vertue, and to fruſtrate the Tendency of natural Corruption.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By this means there would be made deep and liſting Impreſſions, concerning the Obligations of our moſt holy Faith. For how can the Solemnity, which attends Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation be eaſily forgot? Tn the Preſence of God, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and a publick Aſſembly, we declare our ſelves Chriſtians, own our baptiſmal Vow, and promiſe we will ever ſincerely endeavour to perform it. Now how can we chuſe but remember this, through the whole Courſe of our Lives? What a mighty influence muſt this day al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have upon our thoughts? what Encouragements to Vertue, and what Arguments againſt Vice, muſt we hence needs derive? In the Primitive times of Chriſtianity, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dult baptized had a white Garment delivered to them, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after Baptiſm; this Garment they wore for a week, and then 'twas depoſited in the Church? 'Twas to ſignifie the Innocency, which ſhould belong to a Chriſtian, and to fix that Impreſſion upon their thoughts. Now the Office of Confirmation muſt needs anſwer this excellent Deſign, can't fail of impreſſing lively and laſting ideas of our Duty, muſt neceſſarily mind us of, and oblige us to, perform it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Doctrine of Confirmation rightly attended to, would prove an admirable means, to eaſe the thoughts of thoſe, who are Sureties for Infants at their Baptiſm, and to acquit them from their heavy Charge: For ſo great is the Obligation, which ſuch perſons take upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that nothing but a ſtrange Stupidity, and the Apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy which is owing to an habit of ſinning, can render them inſenſible; they ſolemnly in the name of the Child, promiſe and vow to God, that they will renounce the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101428:16"/>World, the Fleſh, and the Devil. This, beſides what their own Obligations to Chriſtianity engage them to, they are bound to perform, and ſincerely to endeavour, that the Child be made ſenſible of this their Obligation, which till they have performed, and the Child at Confirmation has relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them from their Vows, by taking it upon it ſelf, they ſtand bound to God, and upon the failure of their Promiſe, are continually expoſed to the Divine Diſpleaſure. How happy would it be for the Chriſtian World, were theſe things rightly conſidered? How evidently would Piety proſper among us? and how apparently would that only true Felicity of mankind, Peace of Conſcience, make Men happy? In ſhort, theſe our Vows to God are very ſolemn, and of great moment; and as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, the infinitely holy God, can't poſſibly take Pleaſure in ſuch Fools, who take no care to perform them; ſo that whoever neglects this Vow, how inſenſible ſoever he may be of his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, he can't enjoy any true quiet, or peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By the right uſe of Confirmation, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> greateſt Objection would be fully and naturally anſwered; it would ſilence their great Clamour about Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: For tho' the Practiſe of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in reference to Circumciſion; and the undeniable Cuſtom of baptizing Infants, even from ultimate Antiquity, in the Chriſtian Church; and the ſeveral plain Declarations of Scripture in this Caſe, are ſufficient evidence, yet the Doctrine of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, duely attended to, may juſtly put an end to all their Quarrel. Here the baptized Perſon, with all the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity imaginable in his own Perſon, owns his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Vow, profeſſes himſelf a Chriſtian, and declares he will ever by the Grace of God, endeavour to live ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that moſt holy Faith. In ſhort, by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Confirmation, this Objection of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:101428:16"/>ſeems to have been anticipated; and perhaps I may add, that the due uſe of it in the early Times of Chriſtianity, was the reaſon we then heard of no ſuch Party in the World. But When through the Decay of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Corruption of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation began to be ſlighted, and wrong applied; then did an Oppoſition to Infant Baptiſm, perhaps not unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, take its beginning.</p>
            <p n="7">7. By the right uſe of Confirmation, the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, would be more duely frequented. This great poſitive Command of the Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by him to ſuch admirable Purpoſe, among his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Followers, would, by the Means of that Preparation of Thought, which Confirmation requires, and which by that Divine Aſſignment is communicated, be highly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, and piouſly approached. It would by this Means, in a great Meaſure gain its priſtine Honour, and Intenſeneſs of Devotion: The want of which among us is very diſmal to conſider; and ſeems ſadly to foretel the Ruine of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. But,</p>
            <p n="8">8. Were the Doctrine of Confirmation duely attended<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, the Unity of the Church of God would be more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily maintained: Men would bluſh to leave the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of that Church, upon a ſlight, or no conſideration, which they ſo ſolemnly owned, when they were confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. They could not pick Quarrels out of a Lightneſs of Temper, a Deſire of Novelty: in ſhort, ſuch an Influence muſt the Adminiſtration of this Office have upon Men's Thoughts, that nothing leſs than the being guilty of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Sin, (which is the onely juſt Cauſe of Separation) would divide them from that Communion, which they once with ſuch Solemnity choſe to themſelves. Now how happy an Effect would this be? how acceptable to God? how pleaſing among Men? how like even to Heaven? To
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101428:17"/>conclude, Were the Doctrine of Confirmation duly valued, it would lay the Foundation for ſuch a ſincere Practice of Chiriſtianity, as would promote both our publick, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Peace and Happineſs; would pat a ſtop to that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign Influence, which Impiety, and Prophaneneſs hive up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us: And finally would bleſs the World, as the Holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> deſigned his admirable Religion ſhould do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All which; God of his Infinite Mercy grant us, for the alone Sake of the ſame Meritorious</hi> Jeſus; <hi>to whom with the Father, and the Holy Spirit, three Perſons and One God, be all Honour and Glory, Might, Majeſty, and Dominion, now and for ever</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101428:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
